<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Research on SASIP</title><link>https://sasip-climate.github.io/research/</link><description>Recent content in Research on SASIP</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://sasip-climate.github.io/research/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>WP1 Sea Ice Code Development — Optimization</title><link>https://sasip-climate.github.io/research/work-package-one/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sasip-climate.github.io/research/work-package-one/</guid><description>Our ambition is to develop of the neXtSIM sea ice model to run on massively parallel architectures, making its inclusion in an Earth System Model feasible. To accomplish this we will improve the numerical efficiency of its underlying C++ code and perform exploratory work to enable continued improvements in model efficiency beyond those immediately necessary for integrating it into a climate model.
WP1 is divided into five tasks, two of which address known shortcomings of the current model version, two which aim to push the numerical performanc eof the model further and one concerned with evaluating the physical consistency of the results obtained with the updated model code.</description></item><item><title>WP2 Sea Ice Rheology — Physical Parameterizations</title><link>https://sasip-climate.github.io/research/work-package-two/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sasip-climate.github.io/research/work-package-two/</guid><description>We are concerned with enhancing the mechanical parametrizations of the rheological framework employed in the continuum sea ice model developed within SASIP.
The aim is to develop physically sound parametrizations that can translate the dependence of the mechanical strength of the ice cover at the large scale (10-100 km) on both its granular concentration and level of fracturing at the small scale (&amp;lt; 10 km), thereby enabling the MEB framework to represent adequately the spatial and temporal mechanical transition between a dense, brittle ice pack and a loose, granular aggregate of ice floes reminiscent of the Marginal Ice Zone.</description></item><item><title>WP3 Ice–Ocean Interactions</title><link>https://sasip-climate.github.io/research/work-package-three/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sasip-climate.github.io/research/work-package-three/</guid><description>Across a single sea ice floe just a few meters wide, upper ocean exchanges of heat, momentum, and freshwater can vary by two orders of magnitude. Ocean surface waves flex and fragment sea ice altering its geometry, driving ocean mixing and sea ice melting. These effects, and their important impact on sea ice and ocean variability, are forced by variations in sea ice geometry much smaller than a continuum climate model grid scale.</description></item><item><title>WP4 Data Assimilation — Machine Learning</title><link>https://sasip-climate.github.io/research/work-package-four/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sasip-climate.github.io/research/work-package-four/</guid><description>We complement the model development efforts of the other WPs by providing data-constrained sea ice analyses. To meet this goal we shall develop specific and novel data assimilation (DA) methods adapted to the new continuum version of the sea ice model neXtSIM discretised using discontinuous Galerkin method. WP4 will also use state-of-the art DA and machine learning (ML) methods not used in sea ice modeling before, and develop novel approaches for the unique computational and physical features of neXtSIM.</description></item><item><title>WP5 Climate Implications</title><link>https://sasip-climate.github.io/research/work-package-five/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sasip-climate.github.io/research/work-package-five/</guid><description>We focuses on assessing the climate implications of the state-of-the-art sea ice modelling framework being developed during SASIP
Our work is devided into two parts:
Building a global fully coupled GCM including the new sea ice modeling system Fully-coupled climate impacts using SASIP efforts People involved in WP2:
Rym Msadek (rym.msadek(at)cerfacs.fr) Sophie Valcke (sophie.valcke(at)cerfacs.fr) Éric Maisonnave (eric.maisonnave(at)cerfacs.fr) Laurent Terray (laurent.terray(at)cerfac.fr) Romain Bourdallé-Badie (rbourdal(at)mercator-ocean.fr) Pierre Rampal (pierre.rampal(at)univ-grenoble-alpes.fr) Christopher Horvat (christopher_horvat(at)brown.</description></item></channel></rss>