<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>News on SASIP</title><link>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/</link><description>Recent content in News on SASIP</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>June 30th, 2021 - SASIP Webinar #2</title><link>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/webinar-chris/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/webinar-chris/</guid><description>The second SASIP Webinar will be held remotely on June 30th, 2021 starting at 10am CEST.
The presentation entitled Observing and Modelling the Marginal Ice Zone will be made by Christopher Horvat.
The recording of the presentation is available here : https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=z8YAugYNNKU and the presentation&amp;rsquo;s slides are available here : https://www.dropbox.com/s/8dnypn9byzdfn2g/SASIP-MIZ.pptx?dl=0</description></item><item><title>June 10th, 2021 - New SASIP-related paper</title><link>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/paper-vero/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/paper-vero/</guid><description>This paper discusses the numerical challenges pertaining to the treatment of advection in models that represent both the extreme gradients associated with brittle fracturing and the large, permanent post-fracture deformations in complex geomaterials. When developing the Maxwell-Elasto-Brittle rheological model for sea ice, we chose to go Eulerian and to make use of the Discontinuous Galerkin methods. Their implementation and first results are presented here. This work will be pursued within SASIP, Work Package 1.</description></item><item><title>May 20th, 2021 - SASIP Webinar #1</title><link>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/webinar-vero/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/webinar-vero/</guid><description>The first SASIP Webinar will be held remotely on May 20th, 2021 starting at 3pm CEST.
The presentation entitled A continuum viscous-elastic-brittle, FEM/DG model for the fracture and drift of sea ice will be made by Véronique Dansereau.
Here is the abstract for further information:
The thin ice covering the polar oceans is a complex geomaterial that is constantly breaking and moving under the action of the winds and ocean currents.</description></item><item><title>April 20th, 2021 - New SASIP-related paper</title><link>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/nature-chris/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/nature-chris/</guid><description>Read more about how sea ice models should be compared based on how they represent the marginal ice zone, not sea ice extent or area. One of SASIP&amp;rsquo;s primary goals is to improve the representation of marginal ice zones, especially wave-ice and floe size interactions</description></item><item><title>May 11th and 12th, 2021 - Kick-off meeting</title><link>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/kick-off/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/kick-off/</guid><description/></item></channel></rss>