<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>SASIP news on SASIP</title><link>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/</link><description>Recent content in SASIP news on SASIP</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 13 Jun 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>2024 SASIP Annual Meeting</title><link>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/2024-06-13_annual-meeting/</link><pubDate>Thu, 13 Jun 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/2024-06-13_annual-meeting/</guid><description>The 2024 SASIP annual meeting took place in Bologna, Italy, from June 4 to 6, 2024. Three days of inspiring talks and posters as well as productive working groups.
It was nice to see you all in person, thanks for joining!
This event gathered 60 participants of 7 countries (Italy, France, US, New Zealand, UK, Norway, Germany) from all the institutions of the SASIP consortium.
We will soon post here the recordings of the science talks and discussions.</description></item><item><title>June Newsletter</title><link>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/june-newsletter/</link><pubDate>Tue, 04 Jun 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/june-newsletter/</guid><description>SASIP June Newsletter Campaign URL Copy Twitter 0 tweets Subscribe Past Issues RSS Translate English العربية Afrikaans беларуская мова български català 中文（简体） 中文（繁體） Hrvatski Česky Dansk eesti&amp;nbsp;keel Nederlands Suomi Fran&amp;ccedil;ais Deutsch &amp;Epsilon;&amp;lambda;&amp;lambda;&amp;eta;&amp;nu;&amp;iota;&amp;kappa;ή हिन्दी Magyar Gaeilge Indonesia íslenska Italiano 日本語 ភាសាខ្មែរ 한국어 македонски&amp;nbsp;јазик بهاس ملايو Malti Norsk Polski Portugu&amp;ecirc;s Portugu&amp;ecirc;s&amp;nbsp;-&amp;nbsp;Portugal Rom&amp;acirc;nă Русский Espa&amp;ntilde;ol Kiswahili Svenska עברית Lietuvių latviešu slovenčina slovenščina српски தமிழ் ภาษาไทย Türkçe Filipino украї́нська Tiếng&amp;nbsp;Việt Latest news from SASIP View this email in your browser</description></item><item><title>SASIP May Webinar - Robert Jendersie</title><link>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/2024-05-24_may_webinar/</link><pubDate>Fri, 24 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/2024-05-24_may_webinar/</guid><description>Robert Jendersie, PhD student from the University of Magdeburg, presented his work as part of the SASIP May webinar.
Check the recording of the meeting:</description></item><item><title>May Newsletter</title><link>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/2024-05-06_may_newsletter/</link><pubDate>Mon, 06 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/2024-05-06_may_newsletter/</guid><description>SASIP May Newsletter Campaign URL Copy Twitter 0 tweets Subscribe Past Issues RSS Translate English العربية Afrikaans беларуская мова български català 中文（简体） 中文（繁體） Hrvatski Česky Dansk eesti&amp;nbsp;keel Nederlands Suomi Fran&amp;ccedil;ais Deutsch &amp;Epsilon;&amp;lambda;&amp;lambda;&amp;eta;&amp;nu;&amp;iota;&amp;kappa;ή हिन्दी Magyar Gaeilge Indonesia íslenska Italiano 日本語 ភាសាខ្មែរ 한국어 македонски&amp;nbsp;јазик بهاس ملايو Malti Norsk Polski Portugu&amp;ecirc;s Portugu&amp;ecirc;s&amp;nbsp;-&amp;nbsp;Portugal Rom&amp;acirc;nă Русский Espa&amp;ntilde;ol Kiswahili Svenska עברית Lietuvių latviešu slovenčina slovenščina српски தமிழ் ภาษาไทย Türkçe Filipino украї́нська Tiếng&amp;nbsp;Việt Latest news from SASIP View this email in your browser</description></item><item><title>SASIP April Webinar - Tobias Finn</title><link>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/2024-04-26_april_webinar/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 Apr 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/2024-04-26_april_webinar/</guid><description>Tobias Finn, Postdoc at École des Ponts ParisTech and working on WP4 presents his latest research on surrogate modelling of sea-ice models with generative deep learning.
Check the recording of the meeting:</description></item><item><title>Do AI models produce better weather forecasts than physics-based models? A quantitative evaluation case study of Storm Ciarán</title><link>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/2024-04-22_charlton-perez_driscoll_2024/</link><pubDate>Mon, 22 Apr 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/2024-04-22_charlton-perez_driscoll_2024/</guid><description>Do AI models produce better weather forecasts than physics-based models? A quantitative evaluation case study of Storm Ciarán published in npj Climate and Atmospheric Science.
Andrew J. Charlton-Perez and co-authors, including Simon Driscoll, investigate the ability of many of the world&amp;rsquo;s leading NWP and AI weather forecasting models in their ability to simulate Storm Ciaran. AI models are essentially indistinguishable from NWP models in the storm track and MSLP fields analysed, and many important dynamical features are well captured by the AI models.</description></item><item><title>Data-driven surrogate modeling of high-resolution sea-ice thickness in the Arctic</title><link>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/durand-2024/</link><pubDate>Thu, 18 Apr 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/durand-2024/</guid><description>Data-driven surrogate modeling of high-resolution sea-ice thickness in the Arctic by Charlotte Durand, Tobias Sebastian Finn, Alban Farchi, Marc Bocquet, Guillaume Boutin, and Einar Ólason published in the Cryosphere.
In this article, Charlotte Durand et al. focus on predicting Arctic-wide sea-ice thickness using surrogate modeling with deep learning. The model has a predictive power of 12 h up to 6 months. For this forecast horizon, persistence and daily climatology are systematically outperformed, a result of learned thermodynamics and advection.</description></item><item><title>April Newsletter: EGU special edition!</title><link>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/2024-04-08_april-newsletter/</link><pubDate>Mon, 08 Apr 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/2024-04-08_april-newsletter/</guid><description>SASIP April Newsletter Campaign URL Copy Twitter 0 tweets Subscribe Past Issues RSS Translate English العربية Afrikaans беларуская мова български català 中文（简体） 中文（繁體） Hrvatski Česky Dansk eesti&amp;nbsp;keel Nederlands Suomi Fran&amp;ccedil;ais Deutsch &amp;Epsilon;&amp;lambda;&amp;lambda;&amp;eta;&amp;nu;&amp;iota;&amp;kappa;ή हिन्दी Magyar Gaeilge Indonesia íslenska Italiano 日本語 ភាសាខ្មែរ 한국어 македонски&amp;nbsp;јазик بهاس ملايو Malti Norsk Polski Portugu&amp;ecirc;s Portugu&amp;ecirc;s&amp;nbsp;-&amp;nbsp;Portugal Rom&amp;acirc;nă Русский Espa&amp;ntilde;ol Kiswahili Svenska עברית Lietuvių latviešu slovenčina slovenščina српски தமிழ் ภาษาไทย Türkçe Filipino украї́нська Tiếng&amp;nbsp;Việt Latest news from SASIP View this email in your browser</description></item><item><title>SASIP March Webinar - Prof. Sebastian Reich</title><link>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/march_webinar/</link><pubDate>Tue, 19 Mar 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/march_webinar/</guid><description>Sebastian Reich, Professor of Numerical analysis and expert in Data Assimilation from the University of Potsdam presented his research on Particle-Based Algorithms for Stochastic Optimal Control.
Check the recording of the meeting:</description></item><item><title>Parameter sensitivity analysis of a sea ice melt pond parametrisation and its emulation using neural networks</title><link>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/2024-03-16_driscoll_2024/</link><pubDate>Sat, 16 Mar 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/2024-03-16_driscoll_2024/</guid><description>Parameter sensitivity analysis of a sea ice melt pond parametrisation and its emulation using neural networks by Simon Driscoll, Alberto Carrassi, Julien Brajard, Laurent Bertino, Marc Bocquet, Einar Örn Ólason, published in the Journal of Computational Science.
Simon Driscoll et al. show through a global sensitivity analysis and analysis of perturbed parameter ensembles that a state-of-the-art sea ice model, Icepack, demonstrates a substantial sensitivity to its level-ice melt pond parametrisation. To reduce this uncertainty, they investigated the possibility of data driven approaches to learn and replace parametrisations.</description></item><item><title>March Newsletter</title><link>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/march_newsletter/</link><pubDate>Fri, 15 Mar 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/march_newsletter/</guid><description>SASIP March Newsletter Campaign URL Copy Twitter 0 tweets Subscribe Past Issues RSS Translate English العربية Afrikaans беларуская мова български català 中文（简体） 中文（繁體） Hrvatski Česky Dansk eesti&amp;nbsp;keel Nederlands Suomi Fran&amp;ccedil;ais Deutsch &amp;Epsilon;&amp;lambda;&amp;lambda;&amp;eta;&amp;nu;&amp;iota;&amp;kappa;ή हिन्दी Magyar Gaeilge Indonesia íslenska Italiano 日本語 ភាសាខ្មែរ 한국어 македонски&amp;nbsp;јазик بهاس ملايو Malti Norsk Polski Portugu&amp;ecirc;s Portugu&amp;ecirc;s&amp;nbsp;-&amp;nbsp;Portugal Rom&amp;acirc;nă Русский Espa&amp;ntilde;ol Kiswahili Svenska עברית Lietuvių latviešu slovenčina slovenščina српски தமிழ் ภาษาไทย Türkçe Filipino украї́нська Tiếng&amp;nbsp;Việt Latest news from SASIP View this email in your browser</description></item><item><title>Interview with Romain Caneill, Postdoc, CNRS</title><link>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/interview_romain_caneill/</link><pubDate>Thu, 07 Mar 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/interview_romain_caneill/</guid><description>Romain Caneill, postdoc at the French National Center for Scientific Research (CNRS), recently joined SASIP to work on sea-ice rheology (WP2) and climate implications WP5. He accepted to share his scientific history, vision of science, motivations and hopes.
&amp;ldquo;I hope that at the end of the SASIP project, the ocean-atmosphere community will acknowledge the important role of sea ice and the fact that its dynamics need to be well represented in climate models.</description></item><item><title>Towards a GPU-Parallelization of the neXtSIM-DG Dynamical Core</title><link>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/jendersie_preprint_2024/</link><pubDate>Wed, 28 Feb 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/jendersie_preprint_2024/</guid><description>Towards a GPU-Parallelization of the neXtSIM-DG Dynamical Core by Jendersie et al.
In recent years, a number of frameworks have become available that promise to simplify general purpose GPU programming. In this new preprint, Robert Jendersie and colleagues compare multiple such frameworks, including CUDA, SYCL, Kokkos and PyTorch, for the parallelization of \nextsim, a finite-element based dynamical core for sea ice. They evaluate the different approaches according to their usability and performance.</description></item><item><title>SASIP February Webinar - Francesca Vittorioso</title><link>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/webinar_february_2024/</link><pubDate>Wed, 21 Feb 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/webinar_february_2024/</guid><description>On February 21st, Francesca Vittorioso presented her latest research on the Contribution of the assimilation of MTG/IRS radiances for the characterisation of the atmospheric chemical composition over Europe.
See her interview here
Check the recording of the meeting :</description></item><item><title>Investigating ecosystem connections in the shelf sea environment using complex networks</title><link>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/2024-02-08_higgs_carassi_2024/</link><pubDate>Thu, 08 Feb 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/2024-02-08_higgs_carassi_2024/</guid><description>Investigating ecosystem connections in the shelf sea environment using complex networks by Ieuan Higgs, Jozef Skákala, Ross Bannister, Alberto Carrassi, and Stefano Ciavatta, published in Biogeosciences.
Use of complex network to disentagle the bio-geochemistry relation in the ocean.
https://doi.org/10.5194/bg-21-731-2024
Fig.1 (from Higgs et al.):The Atlantic Margin Model (AMM7) domain used in this study. The figure also shows the ocean bathymetry of the North West European Shelf.</description></item><item><title>February Newsletter</title><link>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/2024-02-06_february_newsletter/</link><pubDate>Tue, 06 Feb 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/2024-02-06_february_newsletter/</guid><description>SASIP February Newsletter Campaign URL Copy Twitter 0 tweets Subscribe Past Issues RSS Translate English العربية Afrikaans беларуская мова български català 中文（简体） 中文（繁體） Hrvatski Česky Dansk eesti&amp;nbsp;keel Nederlands Suomi Fran&amp;ccedil;ais Deutsch &amp;Epsilon;&amp;lambda;&amp;lambda;&amp;eta;&amp;nu;&amp;iota;&amp;kappa;ή हिन्दी Magyar Gaeilge Indonesia íslenska Italiano 日本語 ភាសាខ្មែរ 한국어 македонски&amp;nbsp;јазик بهاس ملايو Malti Norsk Polski Portugu&amp;ecirc;s Portugu&amp;ecirc;s&amp;nbsp;-&amp;nbsp;Portugal Rom&amp;acirc;nă Русский Espa&amp;ntilde;ol Kiswahili Svenska עברית Lietuvių latviešu slovenčina slovenščina српски தமிழ் ภาษาไทย Türkçe Filipino украї́нська Tiếng&amp;nbsp;Việt Latest news from SASIP View this email in your browser</description></item><item><title>Interview with Francesca Vittorioso, Postdoc, University of Bologna</title><link>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/interview_francesca/</link><pubDate>Tue, 06 Feb 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/interview_francesca/</guid><description>Francesca Vittorioso, postdoc at the University of Bologna, Italy, recently joined SASIP to work on Data Assimilation. On February 21st, she will give a webinar (register here) presenting her latest research on the Contribution of the assimilation of MTG/IRS radiances for the characterisation of the atmospheric chemical composition over Europe. On this occasion, we asked her to share some of her personal and scientific history.
&amp;ldquo;SASIP will allow a better understanding of the warming of the polar regions.</description></item><item><title>A method for constructing directional surface wave spectra from ICESat-2 altimetry</title><link>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/paper-momme_chris_2024/</link><pubDate>Fri, 19 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/paper-momme_chris_2024/</guid><description>Momme C.Hell and Christopher Horvat have published a new paper paper related to their work in SASIP-WP3:
A method for constructing directional surface wave spectra from ICESat-2 altimetry, 2024, The Cryosphere.
Surface waves impact Sea Ice Fracture in the MIZ, but wave attenuation in sea ice is one of the least constrained processes in current sea ice models. We hear how a method that provide 2D wave spectra in sea ice along ICESat-2 tracks.</description></item><item><title>January Newsletter</title><link>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/january_newsletter/</link><pubDate>Thu, 18 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/january_newsletter/</guid><description>SASIP January Newsletter Campaign URL Copy Twitter 0 tweets Subscribe Past Issues RSS Translate English العربية Afrikaans беларуская мова български català 中文（简体） 中文（繁體） Hrvatski Česky Dansk eesti&amp;nbsp;keel Nederlands Suomi Fran&amp;ccedil;ais Deutsch &amp;Epsilon;&amp;lambda;&amp;lambda;&amp;eta;&amp;nu;&amp;iota;&amp;kappa;ή हिन्दी Magyar Gaeilge Indonesia íslenska Italiano 日本語 ភាសាខ្មែរ 한국어 македонски&amp;nbsp;јазик بهاس ملايو Malti Norsk Polski Portugu&amp;ecirc;s Portugu&amp;ecirc;s&amp;nbsp;-&amp;nbsp;Portugal Rom&amp;acirc;nă Русский Espa&amp;ntilde;ol Kiswahili Svenska עברית Lietuvių latviešu slovenčina slovenščina српски தமிழ் ภาษาไทย Türkçe Filipino украї́нська Tiếng&amp;nbsp;Việt Latest news from SASIP View this email in your browser</description></item><item><title>Implementation of a brittle sea-ice rheology in an Eulerian, finite-difference, C-grid modeling framework: Impact on the simulated deformation of sea-ice in the Arctic</title><link>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/preprint-brodeau-2024/</link><pubDate>Wed, 10 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/preprint-brodeau-2024/</guid><description>Implementation of a brittle sea-ice rheology in an Eulerian, finite-difference, C-grid modeling framework: Impact on the simulated deformation of sea-ice in the Arctic by Laurent Brodeau et al., published in Geoscientific Model Development.
In this new preprint, Laurent Brodeau, Pierre Rampal et al. describe how they achieved the numerical implementation of the Brittle Bingham-Maxwell sea-ice rheology (BBM) into SI3, the sea-ice component of NEMO
https://doi.org/10.5194/gmd-2023-231
Fig.7 (from Brodeau and Rampal):PDFs of the (a) shear, (b) divergence, (c) convergence, and (d) total deformation rates at the 10 km spatial and 3-day temporal scale, for RGPS data and their synthetic counterparts constructed using the simulated sea-ice velocities of SI3-BBM an SI3-aEVP.</description></item><item><title>Video of the month</title><link>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/2024-01-10_january-video/</link><pubDate>Wed, 10 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/2024-01-10_january-video/</guid><description>This month we publish a video provided by S. Brenner @ Brown University, USA.
In a new paper in Geophysical Research Letters, S. Brenner and members of the SASIP team investigate floe-scale effects on ice-ocean boundary layer turbulence. These numerical simulations of the marginal ice zone, produced with the &amp;ldquo;FloeDyn&amp;rdquo; sea ice discrete element model, show sea ice motion together with the underying ocean current field (white/blue colourmap and vector arrows shows), followed by the associated turbulence generation under the ice (cyan/red colourmap).</description></item><item><title>Video of the month</title><link>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/2023-10-11_october-video/</link><pubDate>Wed, 11 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/2023-10-11_october-video/</guid><description>This month we publish a video from work in progress in SASIP-WP4, provided by C. Durand, T. Finn, A. Farchi, M. Bocquet, E. Òlason @ CEREA, École des Ponts.
Fig.: Movie produced by C. Durand, T. Finn, A. Farchi, M. Bocquet, E. Òlason @ CEREA, École des Ponts This is a work in progress in WP4. By using simulation outputs from neXtSIM and some ERA5 reanalysis atmospheric forcings, we trained a neural network to predict the sea-ice thickness up to 12 hours.</description></item><item><title>2023 VESRI Midterm Review Meeting</title><link>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/2023-10-03_versi-midterm-review-meeting/</link><pubDate>Tue, 03 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/2023-10-03_versi-midterm-review-meeting/</guid><description>The 2023 VESRI midterm review meeting took place in Grenoble (02-03 October 2023). After 2 years since the beginning of SASIP, it was time to gather with SASIP and Schmidt Futures team members for the midterm review meeting !
We were extremely pleased to welcome about 35 participants of 7 countries (France, Germany, UK, Italy, Norway, US, New Zealand) from the institutions of the SASIP consortium, as well as reviewers and Schmidt Futures team members.</description></item><item><title>2023 Annual SASIP meeting</title><link>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/2023-06-28_bergen_annual_meeting/</link><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/2023-06-28_bergen_annual_meeting/</guid><description>The 2023 SASIP annual meeting took place in Bergen (27-30 June 2023).
Thank you to all the participants for these 4 days of inspiring science talks and discussions about sea ice!
This year we had about 60 participants of 7 countries (France, US, New Zeland, UK, Norway, Germany, Italy) from all the institutions of the SASIP consortium.
Nice to see each other in person!
The program of these 4 days can be found here: https://cloud.</description></item><item><title>New paper accepted for publication: Cheng et al (2023)</title><link>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/2023-03-22_paper_cheng2023b/</link><pubDate>Wed, 22 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/2023-03-22_paper_cheng2023b/</guid><description>Sibo Cheng et al. have published a new paper paper related to their work in SASIP-WP4:
Machine learning with data assimilation and uncertainty quantification for dynamical systems: a review, accepted for publication in IEEE/CAA Journal of Automatica Sinica.
Sibo Cheng, Cesar Quilodran-Casas, Said Ouala, Alban Farchi, Che Liu, Pierre Tandeo, Ronan Fablet, Didier Lucor, Bertrand Iooss, Julien Brajard, Dunhui Xiao, Tijana Janjic, Weiping Ding, Yike Guo, Alberto Carrassi, Marc Bocquet, Rossella Arcucci</description></item><item><title>New paper under review: Richter et al (2023)</title><link>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/2023-03-09_paper_richter2023/</link><pubDate>Thu, 09 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/2023-03-09_paper_richter2023/</guid><description>Thomas Richter et al. have submitted a new paper related to their work in SASIP:
The neXtSIM-DG dynamical core: A Framework for Higher-order Finite Element Sea Ice Modeling., under review in EGUsphere.
Thomas Richter, Véronique Dansereau, Christian Lessig, and Piotr Minakowski.
https://doi.org/10.5194/egusphere-2023-391.
Fig.11 (from Richter et al 2023): Visualization of the ice concentration on meshes with a spacing of h = 8 km for dG(0) (finite volumes), dG(1) and dG(2).</description></item><item><title>SASIP Webinar #9 - Sukun Cheng - March 22nd 11am</title><link>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/webinar9/</link><pubDate>Tue, 28 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/webinar9/</guid><description>Our SASIP Webinar #9 with Sukun Cheng on the &amp;lsquo;Arctic sea ice data assimilation combining ensemble Kalman filter with a novel Lagrangian sea ice model for the winter 2019-2020&amp;rsquo; took place on March the 22nd at 11am
Abstract :
Advanced data assimilation (DA) methods, widely used in geophysical and climate studies to merge observations with numerical models, can improve the state estimates and consequent forecasts. We interface the deterministic Ensemble Kalman filter (DEnKF) to the Lagrangian sea ice model, neXtSIM.</description></item><item><title>New paper under review: Finn et al (2023)</title><link>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/2023-02-07_paper_finn2023/</link><pubDate>Tue, 07 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/2023-02-07_paper_finn2023/</guid><description>Tobias Finn et al. have published a new paper paper related to their work in SASIP-WP4:
Deep learning of subgrid-scale parametrisations for short-term forecasting of sea-ice dynamics with a Maxwell-Elasto-Brittle rheology., EGUsphere.
Tobias Sebastian Finn, Charlotte Durand, Alban Farchi, Marc Bocquet, Yumeng Chen, Alberto Carrassi and Véronique Dansereau.
https://doi.org/10.5194/egusphere-2022-1342.
Fig.3 (from Finn et al 2023): In our deep learning approach (a), the input fields are projected by a linear projection operator P from their triangular space into a Cartesian space that has a higher resolution, where the U-Net extracts features.</description></item><item><title>New paper: Ayers et al (2023)</title><link>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/2023-02-08_paper_ayers2023/</link><pubDate>Tue, 07 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/2023-02-08_paper_ayers2023/</guid><description>Daniel Ayers et al. have published a new paper paper related to their work in SASIP-WP4:
Supervised machine learning to estimate instabilities in chaotic systems: estimation of local Lyapunov exponents, under review in QJRMS.
Daniel Ayers, Jack Lau, Javier Amezcua, Alberto Carrassi, Varun Ojha.
https://arxiv.org/abs/2202.04944.
Fig.2 (from Ayers et al 2023): A long-time trajectory of the Lorentz63 system coloured by local Lyapunov exponents (LLE) values (top row) shows how LLE values tend to be arranged in the system’s attractor.</description></item><item><title>New paper : Cheng et al (2023)</title><link>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/2023-02-06_paper_cheng2023/</link><pubDate>Mon, 06 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/2023-02-06_paper_cheng2023/</guid><description>Sukun Cheng et al. have published a new paper paper related to their work in SASIP-WP4:
Novel Arctic sea ice data assimilation combining ensemble Kalman filter with a Lagrangian sea ice model, EGUsphere.
Cheng, S., Chen, Y., Aydoğdu, A., Bertino, L., Carrassi, A., Rampal, P., and Jones, C. K. R. T.
https://doi.org/10.5194/egusphere-2022-627.
Fig.1 (from Cheng et al 2023): Flow chart of the ensemble-DA platform. DEnKF: analysis step; neXtSIM: model forecast step; OSI-SAF SIC/CS2SMOS SIT observation: assimilated observations; TOPAZ forecasts and ECMWF forecasts: upstream forcing data for neXtSIM; Field perturbations: see Section 4.</description></item><item><title>New paper: Ólason et al (2022)</title><link>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/2023-02-05_paper_olason2022/</link><pubDate>Sun, 05 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/2023-02-05_paper_olason2022/</guid><description>Einar Ólason et al. have published a new paper paper related to their work in SASIP-WP1:
A New Brittle Rheology and Numerical Framework for Large-Scale Sea-Ice Models., 2022, Journal of Advances in Modeling Earth Systems, 14.
Ólason, Einar, Guillaume Boutin, Anton Korosov, Pierre Rampal, Timothy Williams, Madlen Kimmritz, Véronique Dansereau, and Abdoulaye Samaké.
https://doi.org/10.1029/2021MS002685.
Fig.4 (from Olason et al 2022): Maps of sea ice shear (day−1) for 2 February 2007 as observed by radarsat geophysical processing system and simulated by neXtSIMv2 using the brittle Bingham-Maxwell and mEVP rheologies.</description></item><item><title>New paper: Boutin et al (2022)</title><link>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/2023-02-04_paper_boutin2022/</link><pubDate>Sat, 04 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/2023-02-04_paper_boutin2022/</guid><description>Guillaume Boutin et al. have published a new paper paper related to their work in SASIP-WP3:
Modelling the Arctic Wave-Affected Marginal Ice Zone: A Comparison with ICESat-2 Observations., 2022, Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society A: Mathematical, Physical and Engineering Sciences 380 (September).
Boutin, G., T. Williams, C. Horvat, and L. Brodeau.
https://doi.org/10.1098/rsta.2021.0262.
Fig.2 (from Boutin et al 2022): (a–c) Comparison of the wMIZ between the model (using REF and the maximum 𝐻𝑠 for each month) and IS-2, for the months of February (a), August (b) and November (c) 2019.</description></item><item><title>Video of the month</title><link>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/2023-01-05_january-video/</link><pubDate>Thu, 05 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/2023-01-05_january-video/</guid><description>This month we publish a video from work in progress in SASIP-WP3, provided by by S. Brenner, C. Horvat, A. Lo Piccolo, P. Haul @ Brown University, USA.
Fig.: Movie produced by S. Brenner, C. Horvat, A. Lo Piccolo, P. Haul @ Brown University, USA. Work in progress in SASIP-WP3. These computer simulations of sea ice floes in the marginal ice zone show how they dynamically move and collide in response to the underlying ocean currents (shown with colour and arrows).</description></item><item><title>Video of the month</title><link>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/2022-12-31_december-video/</link><pubDate>Sat, 31 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/2022-12-31_december-video/</guid><description>This month we publish a video from work in progress in SASIP-WP2, provided by Jean-Pierre Auclair @ISTERRE, Grenoble.
Fig.: Movie produced by JP. Auclair @ ISTERRE, Grenoble. It illustrates work in progress in SASIP-WP2 with a 1D simulations of spectral waves entering and fracturing a continuous sea ice cover of 70cm. Fractures occur when the elastic energy of flexion from the ice deformation exceeds the energy required to break the material.</description></item><item><title>SASIP Webinar #8 - Julien Brajard - November 2nd 2pm</title><link>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/webinar8/</link><pubDate>Wed, 02 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/webinar8/</guid><description>Our SASIP Webinar #8 with Julien Brajard on &amp;lsquo;Super resolution of sea ice thickness&amp;rsquo; took place on November the 2nd at 2pm CEST.</description></item><item><title>Video of the month</title><link>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/2022-11-01_november-video/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/2022-11-01_november-video/</guid><description>This month we publish two videos made for illustrative purposes in SASIP-WP0, provided by Laurent Brodeau (CNRS &amp;amp; Datlas), and Stephanie Leroux (Datlas), Grenoble.
Fig: The above movie shows the evolution every 6h of sea-ice concentration, then thickness, then damage in a numerical simulation of the Arctic region featuring the neXtSIM sea-ice model coupled to NEMO/OPA ocean model via the OASIS coupler. Credits: Data from the WIZARD project @ CMEMS_EU. Movie created by S.</description></item><item><title>ICCS Summer School 2022</title><link>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/2022-08-04_iccs_sm2022/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/2022-08-04_iccs_sm2022/</guid><description>The Institute of Computing for Climate Science Summer School
will take place in Cambridge, UK, September 19th-23th 2022.
The summer school is free to attend and open to Schmidt Futures VESRI projects and CliMA, and any ‘friends and family’, i.e., other collaborators / students known to you who would benefit. Please find more info here: https://cambridge-iccs.github.io/summerschool.html</description></item><item><title>2022 Annual SASIP meeting</title><link>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/2022-07-28_annual_meeting/</link><pubDate>Fri, 24 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/2022-07-28_annual_meeting/</guid><description>The 2022 SASIP annual meeting took place in Grenoble (20-23 June 2022).
Thank you to all the participants for these 3 days of inspiring science talks and discussions about sea ice modeling!
This event was the first in-person meeting of the project, and it has gathered 55 participants of 7 countries (France, US, New Zeland, UK, Norway, Germany, Canada) from the 13 institutions of the SASIP consortium.
We will soon post here the recordings of the science talks and discussions.</description></item><item><title>Save the date!</title><link>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/meeting/</link><pubDate>Thu, 16 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/meeting/</guid><description>The SASIP comittee is pleased to welcome all participants for the first in-person meeting next week in Grenoble.
Click here for more informations on the agenda and here for practical details.</description></item><item><title>FloeDyn Code is open!</title><link>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/floedyn-code/</link><pubDate>Wed, 02 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/floedyn-code/</guid><description>This model owes its originality to the fact that it allows simulating ice floes of shapes derived from observations and collisions between these floes in a way that avoids unrealistic interpenetrations and the associated energy dissipation, which makes it a valuable tool for thermodynamic and eventually dynamic parameterization developments within the WP2 and WP3 of SASIP.
The code and documentation can be found here Trimestrial users and developersmeetings will be held from now on: do not hesitate to send an email to stephane.</description></item><item><title>SASIP Webinar #7 - Ivo Passmans - February 23rd 3pm</title><link>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/webinar7/</link><pubDate>Thu, 10 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/webinar7/</guid><description>Our SASIP Webinar #7 with Ivo Passmans on &amp;lsquo;From ensemble 4DVar to Galerkin data assimilation&amp;rsquo; took place on Wednesday 23 February at 3pm CEST.
Check the recording of the meeting :</description></item><item><title>SASIP Webinar #6 - Ludovic Moreau - January 27th 3pm</title><link>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/webinar6/</link><pubDate>Thu, 27 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/webinar6/</guid><description>Our SASIP Webinar #6 with Ludovic Moreau on &amp;lsquo;Monitoring sea ice thickness and elastic properties with seismic noise and deep learning&amp;rsquo; took place on Thursday 22 January at 3pm CEST.
Check the recording of the meeting :</description></item><item><title>Save the date of the next SASIP webinars</title><link>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/savedates/</link><pubDate>Mon, 03 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/savedates/</guid><description>Mark your calendars for our next webinars:
January the 27th by Ludovic Moreau, February the 23rd by Ivo Pasmans.</description></item><item><title>SASIP Webinar #5 - Jean-Pierre Auclair - December 16th 3pm</title><link>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/webinar5/</link><pubDate>Thu, 16 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/webinar5/</guid><description>Our SASIP Webinar #5 with Jean-Pierre Auclair on &amp;lsquo;Studying sea ice dynamics and wave-ice interactions in the marginal ice zone&amp;rsquo; took place on Thursday 16 December at 3pm CEST.
Check the recording of the meeting :
In his talk, Jean-Pierre will showed how the Marginal Ice Zone (MIZ) is a highly dynamic region between the open ocean and the inner ice pack. The ice over this region is subjected to waves, introducing new forces but also changing the ice from a cohesive material to a mobile collection of floes.</description></item><item><title>SASIP Webinar #4 - Tobias Finn - Nov 24th 3pm</title><link>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/webinar4/</link><pubDate>Wed, 24 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/webinar4/</guid><description>Our SASIP Webinar #4 with Tobias Finn on &amp;lsquo;Making the explicit link between Gaussian process regression and ensemble data assimilation&amp;rsquo; took place on Wednesday 24 November at 3pm CEST.
Check the recording of the meeting :
In his talk, Tobias showed how Gaussian process regression, also called Kriging, might help us to learn sub-grid-scale dynamics of sea ice. Starting with linear regressions, he explained in a stepwise manner the reasoning behind this type of machine learning.</description></item><item><title>SASIP Webinar #3 - Polly Smith - Oct 27th 3pm</title><link>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/webinar3/</link><pubDate>Thu, 21 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/webinar3/</guid><description>Our SASIP Webinar #3 with Polly Smith on &amp;lsquo;Data Assimilation for State and Parameter Estimation&amp;rsquo; took place on Wednesday 27 October at 3pm CEST.
After briefly introducing herself and giving a summary of her research experience, Polly described how we can use data assimilation techniques to deliver improved estimates of uncertain, or poorly known, model parameters alongside the model state. She outlined the theory of joint state-parameter estimation and then discuss aspects related to practical implementation of the approach, using examples from some of her previous work.</description></item><item><title>Webinars will be back soon</title><link>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/coming_soon/</link><pubDate>Mon, 04 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/coming_soon/</guid><description>Coming soon:
Polly will speak about data assimilation for parameter estimation, using data assimilation for joint state-parameter estimation, coupled atmosphere-ocean data assimilation.
Tobias will talk about combining data assimilation with machine learning and vice versa, borrowing ideas from ensemble data assimilation for machine learning.
Jean-Pierre will talk about breaking the ice: wave-ice interactions from averages to distinct events and vice-versa.</description></item><item><title>SASIP Webinar #2 - Christopher Horvat</title><link>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/webinar2/</link><pubDate>Wed, 30 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/webinar2/</guid><description>Christopher Horvat talked about Observing and Modelling the Marginal Ice Zone:
Check the recording of the meeting :
And the presentation&amp;rsquo;s slides are available here : https://www.dropbox.com/s/8dnypn9byzdfn2g/SASIP-MIZ.pptx?dl=0</description></item><item><title>New paper: Dansereau et al (2022)</title><link>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/paper-vero/</link><pubDate>Thu, 10 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/paper-vero/</guid><description>Veronique Dansereau et al. from WP2 publishes a SASIP-related paper.
This paperr discusses the numerical challenges pertaining to the treatment of advection in models that represent both the extreme gradients associated with brittle fracturing and the large, permanent post-fracture deformations in complex geomaterials. When developing the Maxwell-Elasto-Brittle rheological model for sea ice, we chose to go Eulerian and to make use of the Discontinuous Galerkin methods. Their implementation and first results are presented here.</description></item><item><title>SASIP Webinar #1 - Véronique Dansereau</title><link>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/webinar1/</link><pubDate>Thu, 20 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/webinar1/</guid><description>Véronique Dansereau talks about a continuum viscous-elastic-brittle, FEM/DG model for the fracture and drift of sea ice
The thin ice covering the polar oceans is a complex geomaterial that is constantly breaking and moving under the action of the winds and ocean currents. Doing so, it also experiences rheological transitions between a brittle solid and a granular fluid regime. A simple continuum mechanical framework was recently developed in the view of representing the dynamics of sea ice in regional and global stand-alone sea ice or coupled climate models.</description></item><item><title>Kick-off meeting</title><link>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/kick-off/</link><pubDate>Tue, 11 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/kick-off/</guid><description/></item><item><title>New paper: Horvat et al (2022)</title><link>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/nature-chris/</link><pubDate>Tue, 20 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/nature-chris/</guid><description>Chris Horvat from WP3 publishes a SASIP-related paper in Nature Communications.
Read more about how sea ice models should be compared based on how they represent the marginal ice zone, not sea ice extent or area. One of SASIP&amp;rsquo;s primary goals is to improve the representation of marginal ice zones, especially wave-ice and floe size interactions.</description></item></channel></rss>