<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Interviews on SASIP</title><link>https://sasip-climate.github.io/categories/interviews/</link><description>Recent content in Interviews on SASIP</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 07 Mar 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://sasip-climate.github.io/categories/interviews/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Interview with Romain Caneill, Postdoc, CNRS</title><link>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/interview_romain_caneill/</link><pubDate>Thu, 07 Mar 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/interview_romain_caneill/</guid><description>Romain Caneill, postdoc at the French National Center for Scientific Research (CNRS), recently joined SASIP to work on sea-ice rheology (WP2) and climate implications WP5. He accepted to share his scientific history, vision of science, motivations and hopes.
&amp;ldquo;I hope that at the end of the SASIP project, the ocean-atmosphere community will acknowledge the important role of sea ice and the fact that its dynamics need to be well represented in climate models.</description></item><item><title>Interview with Francesca Vittorioso, Postdoc, University of Bologna</title><link>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/interview_francesca/</link><pubDate>Tue, 06 Feb 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/interview_francesca/</guid><description>Francesca Vittorioso, postdoc at the University of Bologna, Italy, recently joined SASIP to work on Data Assimilation. On February 21st, she will give a webinar (register here) presenting her latest research on the Contribution of the assimilation of MTG/IRS radiances for the characterisation of the atmospheric chemical composition over Europe. On this occasion, we asked her to share some of her personal and scientific history.
&amp;ldquo;SASIP will allow a better understanding of the warming of the polar regions.</description></item></channel></rss>