<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Vizualisation on SASIP</title><link>https://sasip-climate.github.io/categories/vizualisation/</link><description>Recent content in Vizualisation on SASIP</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 05 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://sasip-climate.github.io/categories/vizualisation/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Video of the month</title><link>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/2023-01-05_january-video/</link><pubDate>Thu, 05 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/2023-01-05_january-video/</guid><description>This month we publish a video from work in progress in SASIP-WP3, provided by by S. Brenner, C. Horvat, A. Lo Piccolo, P. Haul @ Brown University, USA.
Fig.: Movie produced by S. Brenner, C. Horvat, A. Lo Piccolo, P. Haul @ Brown University, USA. Work in progress in SASIP-WP These computer simulations of sea ice floes in the marginal ice zone show how they dynamically move and collide in response to the underlying ocean currents (shown with colour and arrows).</description></item><item><title>Video of the month</title><link>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/2022-12-31_december-video/</link><pubDate>Sat, 31 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/2022-12-31_december-video/</guid><description>This month we publish a video from work in progress in WP2, provided by Jean-Pierre Auclair @ISTERRE, Grenoble.
Fig.: Movie produced by JP. Auclair @ ISTERRE, Grenoble. It illustrates work in progress in SASIP-WP2 with a 1D simulations of spectral waves entering and fracturing a continuous sea ice cover of 70cm. Fractures occur when the elastic energy of flexion from the ice deformation exceeds the energy required to break the material.</description></item><item><title>Video of the month</title><link>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/2022-11-01_november-video/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/2022-11-01_november-video/</guid><description>This month we publish two videos made for illustrative purposes in WP0, provided by Laurent Brodeau (@CNRS @Datlas, and Stephanie Leroux @Datlas, Grenoble.
Fig: The above movie shows the evolution every 6h of sea-ice concentration, then thickness, then damage in a numerical simulation of the Arctic region featuring the neXtSIM sea-ice model coupled to NEMO/OPA ocean model via the OASIS coupler. Credits: Data from the WIZARD project @ CMEMS_EU. Movie created by S.</description></item></channel></rss>