<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Jobs on SASIP</title><link>https://sasip-climate.github.io/jobs/</link><description>Recent content in Jobs on SASIP</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://sasip-climate.github.io/jobs/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>SASIP Job Offer in Grenoble, FR</title><link>https://sasip-climate.github.io/jobs/ige/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sasip-climate.github.io/jobs/ige/</guid><description>3-years researcher or post-doctoral researcher position in Grenoble, France on processes and modelling of the sea ice/ocean/atmosphere system.
Within SASIP project, the successful candidate will focus particularly on the sea ice dynamics simulated by the new neXtSIM-DG model, comparing it to both observations and other existing sea ice models (e.g. SI3 or neXtSIM in its Lagrangian version). In particular, the researcher will evaluate the realism of this dynamics including a new sub-mesh physics parameterization that takes into account ice floe dynamics (developed within SASIP by another team based in Grenoble), and will try to characterize its impact on oceanic or atmospheric boundary layers.</description></item><item><title>SASIP Job Offer in Grenoble, FR</title><link>https://sasip-climate.github.io/jobs/isterre1/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sasip-climate.github.io/jobs/isterre1/</guid><description>18-month post-doctoral researcher position in Grenoble, France on modelling mechanical interactions between waves and sea ice.
Within SASIP project, the successful candidate will focus particularly on (i) implementing new parameterizations in an existing large-scale coupled sea ice-ocean model, NeXtSIM, with the help of a research engineer (ii) validating the new parameterizations on the basis of comparisons with observations of ice deformation and drift (iii) adjusting, if necessary, the mechanical parameterizations according to the results of these comparisons and in the view of the specific needs of regional and global scales sea ice models.</description></item><item><title>SASIP Job Offer in Grenoble, FR</title><link>https://sasip-climate.github.io/jobs/isterre2/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sasip-climate.github.io/jobs/isterre2/</guid><description>24-month post-doctoral researcher position in Grenoble, France on mechanical sea ice modelling.
Within SASIP project, the successful candidate will focus particularly on formulating an equation for the evolution of the Floe Size Distribution (FSD) associated with wave-ice interactions that can be used in large-scale (10-100 km) continuous sea ice models
The researcher/post-doctoral fellow will a work in a group specialized in the mechanics of continuous media and of sea ice in particular, including engineers, PhD students and postdoctoral fellows.</description></item><item><title>SASIP Post-Doc Offer in Bologna, IT</title><link>https://sasip-climate.github.io/jobs/bologna_postdoc/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sasip-climate.github.io/jobs/bologna_postdoc/</guid><description>1 Postdoc (3 years) in the context of the international project SASIP that studies the Arctic changes.
The postdoc will work at the Dept. of Physics of University of Bologna, in close collaboration with our partner at CMCC, to develop a data assimilation scheme for the advanced sea-ice model neXtSIM, both in stand-alone and in its coupled-to-ocean version.
The postdoc will have the chance to be part of a truly multinational research effort and to be in contact (by visiting the project&amp;rsquo;s partners) with collaborators across EU and USA.</description></item><item><title>SASIP PhD Offer in Bologna, IT</title><link>https://sasip-climate.github.io/jobs/bologna_phd/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sasip-climate.github.io/jobs/bologna_phd/</guid><description>1 PhD position (3 years, official opening by May). The position will be offered in the framework of the PhD program &amp;ldquo;Future earth, climate change and societal challenges&amp;rdquo; within the cohort commencing on November 2023.
The student will work in the international project SASIP that studies the Arctic changes: she/he will study combined machine learning and data assimilation method to improve prediction of the Arctic sea-ice, using modern techniques and dataset (both in-situ and remote sensed).</description></item><item><title>SASIP related Job Offer</title><link>https://sasip-climate.github.io/jobs/bologna/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sasip-climate.github.io/jobs/bologna/</guid><description>1-year Postdoc opportunity at the University of Bologna to work on machine learning and data assimilation. The project aims at studying the mechanisms leading to atmospheric convection. Previous experience in data assimilation and machine learning are desirable but not mandatory and background in atmospheric convention and/or dynamical systems is also advantageous.
The project lasts for 1 year but, based on performances, extension for up to two additional years are possible within the same research team.</description></item><item><title>Contact us for more job opportunities</title><link>https://sasip-climate.github.io/jobs/contact-us/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sasip-climate.github.io/jobs/contact-us/</guid><description>You can reach out to office(at)sasip-climate.com</description></item></channel></rss>