<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Publications on SASIP</title><link>https://sasip-climate.github.io/categories/publications/</link><description>Recent content in Publications on SASIP</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 06 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://sasip-climate.github.io/categories/publications/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>New SASIP-WP4 paper (Cheng et al 2023)</title><link>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/2023-02-06_paper_cheng2023/</link><pubDate>Mon, 06 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/2023-02-06_paper_cheng2023/</guid><description>Sukun Cheng et al. have published a new paper paper related to their work in SASIP-WP4:
Cheng, S., Chen, Y., Aydoğdu, A., Bertino, L., Carrassi, A., Rampal, P., and Jones, C. K. R. T.: Novel Arctic sea ice data assimilation combining ensemble Kalman filter with a Lagrangian sea ice model, EGUsphere. Online access here:.</description></item><item><title>New SASIP-related paper</title><link>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/paper-vero/</link><pubDate>Thu, 10 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/paper-vero/</guid><description>Veronique Dansereau et al. from WP2 publishes a SASIP-related paper.
This paperr discusses the numerical challenges pertaining to the treatment of advection in models that represent both the extreme gradients associated with brittle fracturing and the large, permanent post-fracture deformations in complex geomaterials. When developing the Maxwell-Elasto-Brittle rheological model for sea ice, we chose to go Eulerian and to make use of the Discontinuous Galerkin methods. Their implementation and first results are presented here.</description></item><item><title>New SASIP-related paper</title><link>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/nature-chris/</link><pubDate>Tue, 20 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/nature-chris/</guid><description>Chris Horvat from WP3 publishes a SASIP-related paper in Nature Communications.
Read more about how sea ice models should be compared based on how they represent the marginal ice zone, not sea ice extent or area. One of SASIP&amp;rsquo;s primary goals is to improve the representation of marginal ice zones, especially wave-ice and floe size interactions.</description></item></channel></rss>