<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Publications on SASIP</title><link>https://sasip-climate.github.io/categories/publications/</link><description>Recent content in Publications on SASIP</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 28 Feb 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://sasip-climate.github.io/categories/publications/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Towards a GPU-Parallelization of the neXtSIM-DG Dynamical Core</title><link>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/jendersie_preprint_2024/</link><pubDate>Wed, 28 Feb 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/jendersie_preprint_2024/</guid><description>Towards a GPU-Parallelization of the neXtSIM-DG Dynamical Core by Jendersie et al.
In recent years, a number of frameworks have become available that promise to simplify general purpose GPU programming. In this new preprint, Robert Jendersie and colleagues compare multiple such frameworks, including CUDA, SYCL, Kokkos and PyTorch, for the parallelization of \nextsim, a finite-element based dynamical core for sea ice. They evaluate the different approaches according to their usability and performance.</description></item><item><title>Investigating ecosystem connections in the shelf sea environment using complex networks</title><link>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/higgs_carassi_2024/</link><pubDate>Thu, 08 Feb 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/higgs_carassi_2024/</guid><description>Investigating ecosystem connections in the shelf sea environment using complex networks by Ieuan Higgs, Jozef Skákala, Ross Bannister, Alberto Carrassi, and Stefano Ciavatta, published in Biogeosciences.
Use of complex network to disentagle the bio-geochemistry relation in the ocean.
https://doi.org/10.5194/bg-21-731-2024
Fig.1 (from Higgs et al.):The Atlantic Margin Model (AMM7) domain used in this study. The figure also shows the ocean bathymetry of the North West European Shelf.</description></item><item><title>A method for constructing directional surface wave spectra from ICESat-2 altimetry</title><link>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/paper-momme_chris_2024/</link><pubDate>Fri, 19 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/paper-momme_chris_2024/</guid><description>Momme C.Hell and Christopher Horvat have published a new paper paper related to their work in SASIP-WP3:
A method for constructing directional surface wave spectra from ICESat-2 altimetry, 2024, The Cryosphere.
Surface waves impact Sea Ice Fracture in the MIZ, but wave attenuation in sea ice is one of the least constrained processes in current sea ice models. We hear how a method that provide 2D wave spectra in sea ice along ICESat-2 tracks.</description></item><item><title>Implementation of a brittle sea-ice rheology in an Eulerian, finite-difference, C-grid modeling framework: Impact on the simulated deformation of sea-ice in the Arctic</title><link>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/preprint-brodeau-2024/</link><pubDate>Wed, 10 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/preprint-brodeau-2024/</guid><description>Implementation of a brittle sea-ice rheology in an Eulerian, finite-difference, C-grid modeling framework: Impact on the simulated deformation of sea-ice in the Arctic by Laurent Brodeau et al., published in Geoscientific Model Development.
In this new preprint, Laurent Brodeau, Pierre Rampal et al. describe how they achieved the numerical implementation of the Brittle Bingham-Maxwell sea-ice rheology (BBM) into SI3, the sea-ice component of NEMO
https://doi.org/10.5194/gmd-2023-231
Fig.7 (from Brodeau and Rampal):PDFs of the (a) shear, (b) divergence, (c) convergence, and (d) total deformation rates at the 10 km spatial and 3-day temporal scale, for RGPS data and their synthetic counterparts constructed using the simulated sea-ice velocities of SI3-BBM an SI3-aEVP.</description></item><item><title>New paper accepted for publication: Cheng et al (2023)</title><link>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/2023-03-22_paper_cheng2023b/</link><pubDate>Wed, 22 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/2023-03-22_paper_cheng2023b/</guid><description>Sibo Cheng et al. have published a new paper paper related to their work in SASIP-WP4:
Machine learning with data assimilation and uncertainty quantification for dynamical systems: a review, accepted for publication in IEEE/CAA Journal of Automatica Sinica.
Sibo Cheng, Cesar Quilodran-Casas, Said Ouala, Alban Farchi, Che Liu, Pierre Tandeo, Ronan Fablet, Didier Lucor, Bertrand Iooss, Julien Brajard, Dunhui Xiao, Tijana Janjic, Weiping Ding, Yike Guo, Alberto Carrassi, Marc Bocquet, Rossella Arcucci</description></item><item><title>New paper under review: Richter et al (2023)</title><link>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/2023-03-09_paper_richter2023/</link><pubDate>Thu, 09 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/2023-03-09_paper_richter2023/</guid><description>Thomas Richter et al. have submitted a new paper related to their work in SASIP:
The neXtSIM-DG dynamical core: A Framework for Higher-order Finite Element Sea Ice Modeling., under review in EGUsphere.
Thomas Richter, Véronique Dansereau, Christian Lessig, and Piotr Minakowski.
https://doi.org/10.5194/egusphere-2023-391.
Fig.11 (from Richter et al 2023): Visualization of the ice concentration on meshes with a spacing of h = 8 km for dG(0) (finite volumes), dG(1) and dG(2).</description></item><item><title>New paper under review: Finn et al (2023)</title><link>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/2023-02-07_paper_finn2023/</link><pubDate>Tue, 07 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/2023-02-07_paper_finn2023/</guid><description>Tobias Finn et al. have published a new paper paper related to their work in SASIP-WP4:
Deep learning of subgrid-scale parametrisations for short-term forecasting of sea-ice dynamics with a Maxwell-Elasto-Brittle rheology., EGUsphere.
Tobias Sebastian Finn, Charlotte Durand, Alban Farchi, Marc Bocquet, Yumeng Chen, Alberto Carrassi and Véronique Dansereau.
https://doi.org/10.5194/egusphere-2022-1342.
Fig.3 (from Finn et al 2023): In our deep learning approach (a), the input fields are projected by a linear projection operator P from their triangular space into a Cartesian space that has a higher resolution, where the U-Net extracts features.</description></item><item><title>New paper: Ayers et al (2023)</title><link>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/2023-02-08_paper_ayers2023/</link><pubDate>Tue, 07 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/2023-02-08_paper_ayers2023/</guid><description>Daniel Ayers et al. have published a new paper paper related to their work in SASIP-WP4:
Supervised machine learning to estimate instabilities in chaotic systems: estimation of local Lyapunov exponents, under review in QJRMS.
Daniel Ayers, Jack Lau, Javier Amezcua, Alberto Carrassi, Varun Ojha.
https://arxiv.org/abs/2202.04944.
Fig.2 (from Ayers et al 2023): A long-time trajectory of the Lorentz63 system coloured by local Lyapunov exponents (LLE) values (top row) shows how LLE values tend to be arranged in the system’s attractor.</description></item><item><title>New paper : Cheng et al (2023)</title><link>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/2023-02-06_paper_cheng2023/</link><pubDate>Mon, 06 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/2023-02-06_paper_cheng2023/</guid><description>Sukun Cheng et al. have published a new paper paper related to their work in SASIP-WP4:
Novel Arctic sea ice data assimilation combining ensemble Kalman filter with a Lagrangian sea ice model, EGUsphere.
Cheng, S., Chen, Y., Aydoğdu, A., Bertino, L., Carrassi, A., Rampal, P., and Jones, C. K. R. T.
https://doi.org/10.5194/egusphere-2022-627.
Fig.1 (from Cheng et al 2023): Flow chart of the ensemble-DA platform. DEnKF: analysis step; neXtSIM: model forecast step; OSI-SAF SIC/CS2SMOS SIT observation: assimilated observations; TOPAZ forecasts and ECMWF forecasts: upstream forcing data for neXtSIM; Field perturbations: see Section 4.</description></item><item><title>New paper: Ólason et al (2022)</title><link>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/2023-02-05_paper_olason2022/</link><pubDate>Sun, 05 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/2023-02-05_paper_olason2022/</guid><description>Einar Ólason et al. have published a new paper paper related to their work in SASIP-WP1:
A New Brittle Rheology and Numerical Framework for Large-Scale Sea-Ice Models., 2022, Journal of Advances in Modeling Earth Systems, 14.
Ólason, Einar, Guillaume Boutin, Anton Korosov, Pierre Rampal, Timothy Williams, Madlen Kimmritz, Véronique Dansereau, and Abdoulaye Samaké.
https://doi.org/10.1029/2021MS002685.
Fig.4 (from Olason et al 2022): Maps of sea ice shear (day−1) for 2 February 2007 as observed by radarsat geophysical processing system and simulated by neXtSIMv2 using the brittle Bingham-Maxwell and mEVP rheologies.</description></item><item><title>New paper: Boutin et al (2022)</title><link>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/2023-02-04_paper_boutin2022/</link><pubDate>Sat, 04 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/2023-02-04_paper_boutin2022/</guid><description>Guillaume Boutin et al. have published a new paper paper related to their work in SASIP-WP3:
Modelling the Arctic Wave-Affected Marginal Ice Zone: A Comparison with ICESat-2 Observations., 2022, Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society A: Mathematical, Physical and Engineering Sciences 380 (September).
Boutin, G., T. Williams, C. Horvat, and L. Brodeau.
https://doi.org/10.1098/rsta.2021.0262.
Fig.2 (from Boutin et al 2022): (a–c) Comparison of the wMIZ between the model (using REF and the maximum 𝐻𝑠 for each month) and IS-2, for the months of February (a), August (b) and November (c) 2019.</description></item><item><title>New paper: Dansereau et al (2022)</title><link>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/paper-vero/</link><pubDate>Thu, 10 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/paper-vero/</guid><description>Veronique Dansereau et al. from WP2 publishes a SASIP-related paper.
This paperr discusses the numerical challenges pertaining to the treatment of advection in models that represent both the extreme gradients associated with brittle fracturing and the large, permanent post-fracture deformations in complex geomaterials. When developing the Maxwell-Elasto-Brittle rheological model for sea ice, we chose to go Eulerian and to make use of the Discontinuous Galerkin methods. Their implementation and first results are presented here.</description></item><item><title>New paper: Horvat et al (2022)</title><link>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/nature-chris/</link><pubDate>Tue, 20 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sasip-climate.github.io/news/nature-chris/</guid><description>Chris Horvat from WP3 publishes a SASIP-related paper in Nature Communications.
Read more about how sea ice models should be compared based on how they represent the marginal ice zone, not sea ice extent or area. One of SASIP&amp;rsquo;s primary goals is to improve the representation of marginal ice zones, especially wave-ice and floe size interactions.</description></item></channel></rss>